Alex Sheridan

alexandra.sheridan@ined.fr 62 Rue du Faubourg Saint-Denis, 75010 Paris +33~(0)6~66~21~84~84

Updated in January 2024

CURRENT POSITION

French Institute for Demographic Studies (INED), Paris, France

April 2020 - August 2024
Research assistant for project Sogenre: handling data from the Étude Longitudinale Française depuis
l'Enfance (ELFE) and the Millennium Cohort Study (MCS), contributing to the empirical and writing processes,
providing logistical support for the project, creating and managing the project's website using INED software.

Main collaborators: O. Samuel (Paris Nanterre - CRESPPA), C. Brugeilles (CRESPPA), Y. Demoli (UVSQ
- PRINTEMPS, Laboratoire de sociologie quantitative - CREST), C. Hamelin (PRINTEMPS), A. Paillet (Paris
1 - CRESSP), T. Simeon (INED - ELFE).

ACADEMIC WORK EXPERIENCE

INED, Paris, France

July 2022

Translator for project Guide/EuroCohort: translating pilot questionnaires.

INED, Paris, France

April 2021 - July 2022

Data manager for project DICE: handling data from Direction de l'évaluation, de la prospective et de la performance (DEPP), contributing to the empirical and writing processes, creating and managing the project's website using INED software.

Main collaborators: A. Solaz (INED), L. Panico (Sciences Po/CNRS - CRIS), T. Schneider (Leipzig University - Institute of Sociology), E. Washbrook (University of Bristol - School of Education), J. Waldfogel (Columbia University - Columbia School of Social Work), R. Keizer (Erasmus University Rotterdam).

INED, followed by a contract with the OECD, Paris, France

May 2020 - March 2021

Research internship: handling data from Program for International Student Assessment 2018 (PISA), contributing to the empirical process.

Main collaborators: L. Panico, O. Thévenon (OECD - Children's Well-Being Unit), L. Berger (University of Wisconsin-Madison - School of Social Work).

Université Paris Descartes, Paris, France

September 2019 - June 2020

Teaching assistant: Undergraduate macroeconomics classes.

EDUCATION

Paris School of Economics, Paris, France

2018 - 2020

Master's Analysis and Policy in Economics (APE), magna cum laude

Co-accredited by the EHESS, the ENS-PSL, the Ecole des Ponts ParisTech and Université Paris 1 Panthéon-Sorbonne.

Master's thesis: "Older siblings and divorce: Evidence from the British Cohort Study," under the supervision of Andrew Clark (PSE, CNRS).

Specialisation courses: Economics of Well-Being, Economics of Education, Historical Demography, Labour Economics, Migration, Labour Economics and Social Policy, Economic History, Economic History of Labour, Economic Policies and Strategies for Development.

Warwick University, UK (Erasmus programme)

2017 - 2018

Université Paris 1 Panthéon-Sorbonne, Paris, France

2015 - 2018

Undergraduate degree in Economics, magna cum laude

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

Dräger, J., Schneider, T., Olczyk, M., Solaz, A., **Sheridan A.**, Washbrook, E., Perinetti Casoni, V, Kwon S. J., & Waldfogel, J. (2023). "The relevance of tracking and social school composition for growing achievement gaps by parental education in lower secondary school. A longitudinal analysis in France, Germany, the United States, and England." **European Sociological Review.** https://doi.org/10.1093/esr/jcad076.

REVISE AND RESUBMIT

Solaz A., Sheridan A., Panico L., Dräger J., Schneider T., Olczyk M., Washbrook E., Perinetti Casoni V., Kwon S. & Waldfogel J. "Family trajectories, maternal education and achievement gaps: a comparative perspective. Findings on England, France, Germany and the US." Population and Development Review.

Dräger, J., Washbrook, E., Schneider, T., Akabayashi, H., Keizer, R., Solaz, A., Waldfogel, J., de la Rie, S., Kameyama, Y., Kwon, S. J., Nozaki, K., Perinetti Casoni, V., Sano, S., **Sheridan A.** & Shikishima, C. "Crossnational differences in socioeconomic achievement inequality in early primary school: The role of parental education and income in six countries." **AERA Open.** Available as discussion paper on SocArXiv, 18 January 2023. https://doi.org/10.31235/osf.io/hzpwm.

SUBMITTED

Berger L. M., Panico L., **Sheridan A.**, Thévenon O. "Parental Emotional Support and Adolescent Well-Being: A Cross-National Examination of Socio-economic and Gender Gaps based on PISA 2018 Surveys." **Child Indicators Research.**

WORK IN PROGRESS

Samuel O., **Sheridan A.** "Gender and social variations in toilet training: a comparative work in France and in the UK.

Samuel O., **Sheridan A.**, Hamelin C., Demoli Y. "Parental care during the first year of life: gender and social variations in practices and tastes.

Brugeilles C., **Sheridan A.**, Samuel O., Paillet A. "Habiller pour genrer? Pratiques sociales autour du vêtement dans la toute petite enfance."

AWARDS

COORDINATE Transnational Access Visits

October 2023 - November 2023

Three week visit at the Policy Evaluation and Research Unit (PERU) at Manchester Metropolitan University, with a £3500 bursary.

PRESENTATIONS

ELFE unit meeting, INED, December 2023. Oral presentation. "Comparative work on toilet training in France and in the UK: gender and social variations."

Policy Evaluation and Research Unit lunch seminar, Manchester, November 2023. Oral presentation. "Comparative work on toilet training in France and in the UK: gender and social variations."

Children of the noughties: a conference to celebrate 21 years of the Millennium Cohort Study, London, June 2023. Oral presentation. "Parental care during the first year of life: gender and social variations in practices and tastes."

ACADEMIC SERVICE

Co-organiser, Reading group seminar, INED

September 2023 -

Early researchers seminar organised around discussion on Schimel, J. (2012). "Writing science: how to write papers that get cited and proposals that get funded." OUP USA.

Student association president, Paris School of Economics

2019 - 2020

Communication officer for the student association, Paris School of Economics

2018 - 2019

OTHER WORK EXPERIENCE

L'AGEFI, Paris, France

Summer of 2019

Journalism internship: Writing about macroeconomic and financial news.

Phefeni Senior Secondary School, Johannesburg, South Africa

Summer of 2018

Volunteer English teaching assistant as part of the Warwick in Africa charity.

LANGUAGES

English & French: Native (British and French citizenships)

Spanish: Needs refreshing but strong basis

PROGRAMMING & IT

LATEX: Overleaf

R: Data cleaning, Descriptive statistics, Econometrics, RMarkdown, Shiny

Stata: Data cleaning, Descriptive statistics, Econometrics

 ${\bf Git Hub:}$ Website development, GitHub profile: alextranslatus

Zotero